<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "+//IDN docutils.sourceforge.net//DTD Docutils Generic//EN//XML" "http://docutils.sourceforge.net/docs/ref/docutils.dtd">
<!-- Generated by Docutils 0.19 -->
<document source="/Users/clatulip/Documents/RunestoneBooks/ThinkLikeComputer/_sources/Iteration/TheforLoop.rst" xmlns:c="https://www.sphinx-doc.org/" xmlns:changeset="https://www.sphinx-doc.org/" xmlns:citation="https://www.sphinx-doc.org/" xmlns:cpp="https://www.sphinx-doc.org/" xmlns:index="https://www.sphinx-doc.org/" xmlns:js="https://www.sphinx-doc.org/" xmlns:math="https://www.sphinx-doc.org/" xmlns:py="https://www.sphinx-doc.org/" xmlns:rst="https://www.sphinx-doc.org/" xmlns:std="https://www.sphinx-doc.org/">
    <substitution_definition names="blank"><BlankNode></BlankNode></substitution_definition>
    <substitution_definition names="docname"><reference refuri="TheforLoop-source.html">TheforLoop</reference></substitution_definition>
    <comment xml:space="preserve">Copyright (C)  Brad Miller, David Ranum, Jeffrey Elkner, Peter Wentworth, Allen B. Downey, Chris
Meyers, and Dario Mitchell.  Permission is granted to copy, distribute
and/or modify this document under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation
License, Version 1.3 or any later version published by the Free Software
Foundation; with Invariant Sections being Forward, Prefaces, and
Contributor List, no Front-Cover Texts, and no Back-Cover Texts.  A copy of
the license is included in the section entitled "GNU Free Documentation
License".</comment>
    <index entries="['single',\ 'for\ loop',\ 'index-0',\ '',\ None] ['single',\ 'iteration',\ 'index-0',\ '',\ None] ['single',\ 'body',\ 'index-0',\ '',\ None] ['single',\ 'loop;\ for',\ 'index-0',\ '',\ None]" inline="False"></index>
    <target refid="index-0"></target>
    <section ids="the-for-loop index-0" names="the\ for\ loop">
        <title>The <strong>for</strong> Loop</title>

    <video xml:id="forloopvid" youtube="X1-UNHUajfk" width="560" />
            <comment xml:space="preserve">xGSfiZt5cdw   -- this was the old one.</comment>
        <paragraph>Back when we drew the images with turtle it could be quite tedious. If we wanted to draw a square
            then we had to move then turn, move then turn, etc. etc. four times. If we were drawing a hexagon,
            or an octagon, or a polygon with 42 sides, it would have been a nightmare to duplicate all that code.</paragraph>
        <paragraph>In Python, the <strong>for</strong> statement allows us to write programs that implement iteration. As a simple
            example, let’s say we have some friends, and we’d like to send them each an email inviting them to
            our party. We don’t quite know how to send email yet, so for the moment we’ll just print a message
            out to the console to imitate the idea of emailing each friend.</paragraph>

    <program label="ac4_2_1" interactive='activecode' language="python">
    
        <input>
for name in ["Joe", "Amy", "Brad", "Angelina", "Zuki", "Thandi", "Paris"]:
    print("Hi", name, "Please come to my party on Saturday!")
        </input>
<tests>


</tests>

    </program>
        <paragraph>Take a look at the output produced when you press the <literal>run</literal> button. There is one line printed for
            each friend. Here’s how it works:</paragraph>
        <bullet_list bullet="*">
            <list_item>
                <paragraph><strong>name</strong> in this <literal>for</literal> statement is called the <strong>loop variable</strong> or, alternatively, the <strong>iterator variable</strong>.</paragraph>
            </list_item>
            <list_item>
                <paragraph>The list of names in the square brackets is the sequence over which we will iterate.</paragraph>
            </list_item>
            <list_item>
                <paragraph>Line 2  is the <strong>loop body</strong>.  The loop body is always
                    indented. The indentation determines exactly what statements are “in the
                    loop”. The instruction in the loop body is performed
                    one time for each name in the list.</paragraph>
            </list_item>
            <list_item>
                <paragraph>On each <emphasis>iteration</emphasis> or <emphasis>pass</emphasis> of the loop, first a check is done to see if
                    there are still more items to be processed.  If there are none left (this is
                    called the <strong>terminating condition</strong> of the loop), the loop has finished.
                    Program execution continues at the next statement <strong>after</strong> the loop body.</paragraph>
            </list_item>
            <list_item>
                <paragraph>If there are items still to be processed, the loop variable is updated to
                    refer to the next item in the list.  This means, in this case, that the loop
                    body is executed here 7 times, and each time <literal>name</literal> will refer to a different
                    friend.</paragraph>
            </list_item>
            <list_item>
                <paragraph>At the end of each execution of the body of the loop, Python returns
                    to the <literal>for</literal> statement, to see if there are more items to be handled.</paragraph>
            </list_item>
        </bullet_list>
        <paragraph>The overall syntax is <literal>for &lt;loop_var_name&gt; in &lt;sequence&gt;:</literal></paragraph>
        <bullet_list bullet="*">
            <list_item>
                <paragraph>Between the words <strong>for</strong> and <strong>in</strong>, there must be a <strong>variable name</strong> for the loop variable. You can’t put a whole expression there.</paragraph>
            </list_item>
            <list_item>
                <paragraph>A colon is required at the end of the line</paragraph>
            </list_item>
            <list_item>
                <paragraph>After the word <strong>in</strong> and before the colon is an expression that must evaluate to a sequence (e.g, a string or a list). It could be a literal, or a variable name, or a more complex expression. In the example on this page, there is a literal list. You will see examples throughout this chapter that show other ways that a sequence can be specified in a for loop.</paragraph>
            </list_item>
            <list_item>
                <paragraph>Although in this example there is only one instruction in the loop body, there are
                    often multiple instructions.</paragraph>
            </list_item>
        </bullet_list>
    </section>
</document>
