<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "+//IDN docutils.sourceforge.net//DTD Docutils Generic//EN//XML" "http://docutils.sourceforge.net/docs/ref/docutils.dtd">
<!-- Generated by Docutils 0.19 -->
<document source="/Users/clatulip/Documents/RunestoneBooks/ThinkLikeComputer/_sources/DebuggingAndModules/ModulesandGettingHelp.rst" xmlns:c="https://www.sphinx-doc.org/" xmlns:changeset="https://www.sphinx-doc.org/" xmlns:citation="https://www.sphinx-doc.org/" xmlns:cpp="https://www.sphinx-doc.org/" xmlns:index="https://www.sphinx-doc.org/" xmlns:js="https://www.sphinx-doc.org/" xmlns:math="https://www.sphinx-doc.org/" xmlns:py="https://www.sphinx-doc.org/" xmlns:rst="https://www.sphinx-doc.org/" xmlns:std="https://www.sphinx-doc.org/">
    <substitution_definition names="blank"><BlankNode></BlankNode></substitution_definition>
    <substitution_definition names="docname"><reference refuri="ModulesandGettingHelp-source.html">ModulesandGettingHelp</reference></substitution_definition>
    <comment xml:space="preserve">Copyright (C)  Brad Miller, David Ranum, Jeffrey Elkner, Peter Wentworth, Allen B. Downey, Chris
Meyers, and Dario Mitchell.  Permission is granted to copy, distribute
and/or modify this document under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation
License, Version 1.3 or any later version published by the Free Software
Foundation; with Invariant Sections being Forward, Prefaces, and
Contributor List, no Front-Cover Texts, and no Back-Cover Texts.  A copy of
the license is included in the section entitled "GNU Free Documentation
License".</comment>
    <index entries="['single',\ 'documentation\ online',\ 'index-0',\ '',\ None] ['single',\ 'Global\ Module\ Index',\ 'index-0',\ '',\ None] ['single',\ 'module;\ standard',\ 'index-0',\ '',\ None] ['single',\ 'namespace',\ 'index-0',\ '',\ None]" inline="False"></index>
    <target refid="index-0"></target>
    <section ids="modules index-0" names="modules">
        <title>Modules</title>

    <video xml:id="vid_modules" youtube="GCLHuPBtLdQ" width="560" />
            <paragraph>A <strong>module</strong> is a file containing Python definitions and statements intended for
            use in other Python programs. There are many Python modules that come with
            Python as part of the <strong>standard library</strong>. Providing additional functionality through modules allows you to only use the functionality you need when you need it, and it keeps your code cleaner.</paragraph>
        <paragraph>Functions imported as part of a module live in their own <strong>namespace</strong>.  A namespace is simply a space within which all names are distinct from each other. The same name can be reused in different namespaces but two objects can’t have the same name within a single namespace. One example of a namespace is the set of street names within a single city. Many cities have a street called “Main Street”, but it’s very confusing if two streets in the same city have that name! Another example is the folder organization of file systems. You can have a file called todo in your work folder as well as your personal folder, but you know which is which because of the  folder it’s in; each folder has its own namespace for files. Note that human names are not part of a namespace that enforces uniqueness; that’s why governments have invented unique identifiers to assign to people, like passport numbers.</paragraph>
        <paragraph>The  <reference name="Python Documentation" refuri="https://docs.python.org/3/index.html">Python Documentation</reference><target ids="python-documentation" names="python\ documentation" refuri="https://docs.python.org/3/index.html"></target> site is an extremely useful reference for all aspects of Python. The site
            contains a listing of all the standard modules that are available with Python
            (see <reference name="Global Module Index" refuri="https://docs.python.org/3/py-modindex.html">Global Module Index</reference><target ids="global-module-index" names="global\ module\ index" refuri="https://docs.python.org/3/py-modindex.html"></target>). You
            will also see that there is a
            <reference name="Standard Library Reference" refuri="https://docs.python.org/3/library/index.html">Standard Library Reference</reference><target ids="standard-library-reference" names="standard\ library\ reference" refuri="https://docs.python.org/3/library/index.html"></target>
            and a
            <reference name="Tutorial" refuri="https://docs.python.org/3/tutorial/index.html">Tutorial</reference><target ids="tutorial" names="tutorial" refuri="https://docs.python.org/3/tutorial/index.html"></target> as well as
            installation instructions, how-tos, and frequently asked questions.  We
            encourage you to become familiar with this site and to use it often.</paragraph>
        <paragraph>If you have not done so already, take a look at the Global Module Index.  Here
            you will see an alphabetical listing of all the modules that are available as
            part of the standard library.  Find the turtle module.</paragraph>
        <section ids="importing-modules" names="importing\ modules">
            <title>Importing Modules</title>
            <paragraph>In order to use Python modules, you have to <strong>import</strong> them into a Python program. That happens with an import
                statement: the word <literal>import</literal>, and then the <emphasis>name</emphasis> of the module. The name is case-sensitive. Roughly translated to
                English, an import statement says “there’s some code in another file; please make its functions and variables
                available in this file.” More technically, an import statement causes all the code in another file to be executed. Any
                variables that are created and functions that are defined during that execution can then be used in the current file.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>By convention, all <literal>import</literal> commands are put at the very top of your file. They can be put elsewhere, but that can
                lead to some confusion, so it’s best to follow the convention.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>Where do these other files that you can import come from? They may be standard library modules that are available when you install Python, or they may be code files that you wrote yourself, or they could
                be code that someone else wrote and you downloaded on to your computer.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>For example, if you have a file <literal>myprog.py</literal> in directory <literal>~/Desktop/mycode/</literal>, and myprog.py contains a line of
                code <literal>import morecode</literal>, then the python interpreter will look for a file called <literal>morecode.py</literal>, excecute its code,
                and make its variables, objects and functions available for reference in the rest of the code in myprog.py.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>Note that it is <literal>import morecode</literal>, not <literal>import morecode.py</literal>, but the other file has to be called <literal>morecode.py</literal>.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>In some sense, you can think of importing as being similar to including the code from a module into the code you are writing, as depicted in this diagram:</paragraph>
            <image candidates="{'*': 'DebuggingAndModules/Figures/modules_diagram.png'}" uri="DebuggingAndModules/Figures/modules_diagram.png"></image>
            <paragraph>As shown in the diagram, you need to remember that the two sets of code have different namespaces, which typically means that you access the variables and objects in the imported module by using something like <literal>module_name.variable_name</literal>.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>The tests you see in your problem sets make use of a Python module that is in the standard library, called
                <literal>unittest</literal>. Right now, you can’t see the code that causes those tests to run, because we have hidden it from you,
                but in later courses, you will learn how to write your own Unit Tests for code, and to do so, you will need to
                write an import statement at the beginning of your programs. Even before you learn how to write your own tests, you
                will see code for Unit Tests in your problem set files.</paragraph>
            <admonition classes="admonition-don-t-overwrite-standard-library-modules">
                <title>Don’t overwrite standard library modules!</title>
                <paragraph>It is possible to overwrite a standard library. For example, if you create a file <literal>random.py</literal> in the same directory where
                    <literal>myprog.py</literal> lives, and then myprog.py invokes <literal>import random</literal>, it will import <emphasis>your</emphasis> file rather than the
                    standard library module. That’s not usually what you want, so be careful about how you name your python files!</paragraph>
            </admonition>
        </section>
        <section ids="syntax-for-importing-modules-and-functionality" names="syntax\ for\ importing\ modules\ and\ functionality">
            <title>Syntax for Importing Modules and Functionality</title>
            <paragraph>When you see imported modules in a Python program, there are a few variations that have slightly different consequences.</paragraph>
            <enumerated_list enumtype="arabic" prefix="" suffix=".">
                <list_item>
                    <paragraph>The most common is <literal>import morecode</literal>. That imports everything in morecode.py. To invoke a function f1 that is defined in morecode.py, you would write <literal>morecode.f1()</literal>. Note that you have to explicitly mention morecode again, to specify that you want the f1 function from the morecode namespace. If you just write <literal>f1()</literal>, python will look for an f1 that was defined in the current file, rather than in morecode.py.</paragraph>
                </list_item>
                <list_item>
                    <paragraph>You can also give the imported module an alias (a different name, just for when you use it in your program). For example, after executing <literal>import morecode as mc</literal>, you would invoke <literal>f1</literal> as <literal>mc.f1()</literal>. You have now given the <literal>morecode</literal> module the alias <literal>mc</literal>. Programmers often do this to make code easier to type.</paragraph>
                </list_item>
                <list_item>
                    <paragraph>A third possibility for importing occurs when you only want to import SOME of the functionality from a module, and you want to make those objects be part of the current module’s namespace. For example, you could write <literal>from morecode import f1</literal>. Then you could invoke f1 without referencing morecode again: <literal>f1()</literal>.</paragraph>
                </list_item>
            </enumerated_list>
            <admonition classes="admonition-note-python-modules-and-limitations-with-activecode">
                <title>Note: Python modules and limitations with activecode</title>
                <paragraph>Throughout the chapters of this book, activecode windows allow you to practice the Python that you are learning.
                    We mentioned in the first chapter that programming is normally done using some type of development
                    environment and that the
                    activecode used here was strictly to help us learn.  It is not the way we write production programs.</paragraph>
                <paragraph>To that end, it is necessary to mention that many of the  modules available in standard Python
                    will <strong>not</strong> work in the activecode environment.  In fact, only <literal>turtle</literal>, <literal>math</literal>, <literal>random</literal>, and a couple others have been
                    ported at this point.  If you wish to explore any
                    additional modules, you will need to run from the native python interpreter on your computer.</paragraph>
            </admonition>
            <paragraph><strong>Check your understanding</strong></paragraph>

    <exercise label="question3_8_1">
        <statement>

            <paragraph>In Python a module is:</paragraph>

        </statement>
<choices>

            <choice correct='yes'>
                <statement>
                    <p>A file containing Python definitions and statements intended for use in other Python programs.</p>
                </statement>
                <feedback>
                    <p>A module can be reused in different programs.</p>
                </feedback>
            </choice>

            <choice >
                <statement>
                    <p>A separate block of code within a program.</p>
                </statement>
                <feedback>
                    <p>While a module is separate block of code, it is separate from a program.</p>
                </feedback>
            </choice>

            <choice >
                <statement>
                    <p>One line of code in a program.</p>
                </statement>
                <feedback>
                    <p>The call to a feature within a module may be one line of code, but modules are usually multiple lines of code separate from the program.</p>
                </feedback>
            </choice>

            <choice >
                <statement>
                    <p>A file that contains documentation about functions in Python.</p>
                </statement>
                <feedback>
                    <p>Each module has its own documentation, but the module itself is more than just documentation.</p>
                </feedback>
            </choice>
</choices>

    </exercise>

    <exercise label="question3_8_2">
        <statement>

            <paragraph>To find out information on the standard modules available with Python you should:</paragraph>

        </statement>
<choices>

            <choice correct='yes'>
                <statement>
                    <p>Go to the Python Documentation site.</p>
                </statement>
                <feedback>
                    <p>The site contains a listing of all the standard modules that are available with Python.</p>
                </feedback>
            </choice>

            <choice >
                <statement>
                    <p>Look at the import statements of the program you are working with or writing.</p>
                </statement>
                <feedback>
                    <p>The import statements only tell you what modules are currently being used in the program, not how to use them or what they contain.</p>
                </feedback>
            </choice>

            <choice >
                <statement>
                    <p>Ask the professor.</p>
                </statement>
                <feedback>
                    <p>While the professor knows a subset of the modules available in Python, chances are the professor will have to look up the available modules just like you would.</p>
                </feedback>
            </choice>

            <choice >
                <statement>
                    <p>Look in this textbook.</p>
                </statement>
                <feedback>
                    <p>This book only explains a portion of the modules available.  For a full listing you should look elsewhere.</p>
                </feedback>
            </choice>
</choices>

    </exercise>

    <exercise label="question3_8_3">
        <statement>

            <paragraph>True / False:  All standard Python modules will work in activecode.</paragraph>

        </statement>
<choices>

            <choice >
                <statement>
                    <p>True</p>
                </statement>
                <feedback>
                    <p>Only a few modules have been ported to work in activecode at this time.</p>
                </feedback>
            </choice>

            <choice correct='yes'>
                <statement>
                    <p>False</p>
                </statement>
                <feedback>
                    <p>Only a few modules have been ported to work in activecode at this time.</p>
                </feedback>
            </choice>
</choices>

    </exercise>
        </section>
    </section>
</document>
