<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "+//IDN docutils.sourceforge.net//DTD Docutils Generic//EN//XML" "http://docutils.sourceforge.net/docs/ref/docutils.dtd">
<!-- Generated by Docutils 0.19 -->
<document source="/Users/clatulip/Documents/RunestoneBooks/ThinkLikeComputer/_sources/FunctionsParametersScope/LocalGlobalVariablesScope.rst" xmlns:c="https://www.sphinx-doc.org/" xmlns:changeset="https://www.sphinx-doc.org/" xmlns:citation="https://www.sphinx-doc.org/" xmlns:cpp="https://www.sphinx-doc.org/" xmlns:index="https://www.sphinx-doc.org/" xmlns:js="https://www.sphinx-doc.org/" xmlns:math="https://www.sphinx-doc.org/" xmlns:py="https://www.sphinx-doc.org/" xmlns:rst="https://www.sphinx-doc.org/" xmlns:std="https://www.sphinx-doc.org/">
    <substitution_definition names="blank"><BlankNode></BlankNode></substitution_definition>
    <substitution_definition names="docname"><reference refuri="LocalGlobalVariablesScope-source.html">LocalGlobalVariablesScope</reference></substitution_definition>
    <comment xml:space="preserve">Copyright (C)  Brad Miller, David Ranum, Jeffrey Elkner, Peter Wentworth, Allen B. Downey, Chris
Meyers, and Dario Mitchell.  Permission is granted to copy, distribute
and/or modify this document under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation
License, Version 1.3 or any later version published by the Free Software
Foundation; with Invariant Sections being Forward, Prefaces, and
Contributor List, no Front-Cover Texts, and no Back-Cover Texts.  A copy of
the license is included in the section entitled "GNU Free Documentation
License".</comment>
    <index entries="['single',\ 'local\ variable',\ 'index-0',\ '',\ None] ['single',\ 'variable;\ local',\ 'index-0',\ '',\ None] ['single',\ 'lifetime',\ 'index-0',\ '',\ None]" inline="False"></index>
    <target refid="index-0"></target>
    <section ids="scope-local-vs-global-variables index-0" names="scope\ -\ local\ vs\ global\ variables">
        <title>Scope - Local vs Global Variables</title>
        <paragraph>Scope refers to the parts of the program where a variable/object are visible and can be referred to. When you have program
            that has no functions, all of the variables are global. But very few real programs in the world work that way. Most programs
            are divided up into functions, and global variables are passed around, while inside of functions there are also local variables that are used.
            In this section we will take a look at the differences between local and global variables.</paragraph>
        <section ids="variable-and-parameters-are-local" names="variable\ and\ parameters\ are\ local">
            <title>Variable and parameters are local</title>

    <video xml:id="goog_local_vars" youtube="HdFujZpLFVg" width="560" />
                <paragraph>An assignment statement in a function creates a <strong>local variable</strong> for the variable on the left hand side of the
                assignment operator. It is called local because this variable only exists inside the function and you cannot use it
                outside. For example, consider again the <literal>square</literal> function:</paragraph>

    <program label="ac8_7_1" interactive='activecode' language="python">
    
        <input>
def square(x):
    y = x * x
    return y

z = square(10)
print(y)
        </input>
<tests>


</tests>

    </program>
            <paragraph>Try running this in CodeLens. When a function is invoked in CodeLens, the local scope is separated from global scope by
                a blue box. Variables in the local scope will be placed in the blue box while global variables will stay in the global
                frame. If you press the ‘last &gt;&gt;’ button you will see an error message. When we try to use <literal>y</literal> on line 6 (outside the
                function) Python looks for a global variable named <literal>y</literal> but does not find one. This results in the error:
                <literal>Name Error: 'y' is not defined.</literal></paragraph>
            <paragraph>The variable <literal>y</literal> only exists while the function is being executed — we call this its <strong>lifetime</strong>. When the
                execution of the function terminates (returns), the local variables are destroyed. CodeLens helps you visualize this
                because the local variables disappear after the function returns. Go back and step through the statements paying
                particular attention to the variables that are created when the function is called. Note when they are subsequently
                destroyed as the function returns.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>Formal parameters are also local and act like local variables. For example, the lifetime of <literal>x</literal> begins when
                <literal>square</literal> is called, and its lifetime ends when the function completes its execution.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>So it is not possible for a function to set some local variable to a value, complete its execution, and then when it
                is called again next time, recover the local variable. Each call of the function creates new local variables, and
                their lifetimes expire when the function returns to the caller.</paragraph>
        </section>
        <section ids="global-variables" names="global\ variables">
            <title>Global Variables</title>
            <paragraph>Variable names that are at the <emphasis>top-level</emphasis>, not inside any function definition,
                are called global.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>It is legal for a function to access a global variable that isn’t passed in as a parameter. However, this is considered
                <strong>bad form</strong> by nearly all programmers and should be avoided in most cases. This subsection
                includes some examples that illustrate the potential interactions of global and
                local variables. These will help you understand exactly how Python works. Hopefully,
                they will also convince you that things can get pretty confusing when you mix
                local and global variables, and that you really shouldn’t do it.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>Look at the following, nonsensical variation of the square function.</paragraph>

    <program label="ac8_7_2" interactive='activecode' language="python">
    
        <input>
def badsquare(x):
    y = x ** power
    return y

power = 2
result = badsquare(10)
print(result)
        </input>
<tests>


</tests>

    </program>
            <paragraph>Although the <literal>badsquare</literal> function works, it is silly and poorly written. We have done it here to illustrate
                an important rule about how variables are looked up in Python.
                First, Python looks at the variables that are defined as local variables in
                the function.  We call this the <strong>local scope</strong>. If the variable name is not
                found in the local scope, then Python looks at the global variables,
                or <strong>global scope</strong>. This is exactly the case illustrated in the code above.
                <literal>power</literal> is not found locally in <literal>badsquare</literal> but it does exist globally.
                The appropriate way to write this function would be to pass power as a parameter.
                For practice, you should rewrite the badsquare example to have a second parameter called power.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>There is another variation on this theme of local versus global variables. Assignment statements in the local function cannot
                change variables defined outside the function. Consider the following
                CodeLens example:</paragraph>

<program label="clens8_7_1" interactive="codelens" language="python">
    <input>
def powerof(x,p):
    power = p   # Another dumb mistake
    y = x ** power
    return y

power = 3
result = powerof(10,2)
print(result)
    </input>
</program>
            <paragraph>Now step through the code. What do you notice about the values of variable <literal>power</literal>
                in the local scope compared to the variable <literal>power</literal> in the global scope?</paragraph>
            <paragraph>The value of <literal>power</literal> in the local scope was different than the global scope.
                That is because in this example <literal>power</literal> was used on the left hand side of the
                assignment statement <literal>power = p</literal>. When a variable name is used on the
                left hand side of an assignment statement inside a function, Python creates a local variable.
                When a local variable has the same name as a global variable we say that the
                local shadows the global. A <strong>shadow</strong> means that the global variable cannot
                be accessed by Python because the local variable will be found first. This is
                another good reason not to use global variables. As you can see,
                it makes your code confusing and difficult to understand.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>If you really want to change the value of a global variable inside a function,
                you can can do it by explicitly declaring the variable to be global, as in the example
                below. Again, you should <emphasis>not</emphasis> do this in your code. The example is here only
                to cement your understanding of how Python works.</paragraph>

<program label="clens8_7_2" interactive="codelens" language="python">
    <input>
def powerof(x,p):
    global power  # a really...
    power = p     # ...bad idea, but valid code
    y = x ** power
    return y

power = 3
result = powerof(10,2)
print(result)
print(power)
    </input>
</program>
            <paragraph>To cement all of these ideas even further let’s look at one final example.
                Inside the <literal>square</literal> function we are going to make an assignment to the
                parameter <literal>x</literal>  There’s no good reason to do this other than to emphasize
                the fact that the parameter <literal>x</literal> is a local variable.  If you step through
                the example in CodeLens you will see that although <literal>x</literal> is 0 in the local
                variables for <literal>square</literal>, the <literal>x</literal> in the global scope remains 2.  This is confusing
                to many beginning programmers who think that an assignment to a
                formal parameter will cause a change to the value of the variable that was
                used as the actual parameter, especially when the two share the same name.
                But this example demonstrates that that is clearly not how Python operates.</paragraph>

<program label="clens8_7_3" interactive="codelens" language="python">
    <input>
def square(x):
    y = x * x
    x = 0       # assign a new value to the parameter x
    return y

x = 2
z = square(x)
print(z)
    </input>
</program>
            <paragraph><strong>Check Your Understanding</strong></paragraph>

    <exercise label="question8_7_1">
        <statement>

            <paragraph>True or False: Local variables can be referenced outside of the function they were defined in.</paragraph>

        </statement>
<choices>

            <choice >
                <statement>
                    <p>True</p>
                </statement>
                <feedback>
                    <p>Local variables cannot be referenced outside of the function they were defined in.</p>
                </feedback>
            </choice>

            <choice correct='yes'>
                <statement>
                    <p>False</p>
                </statement>
                <feedback>
                    <p>Local variables cannot be referenced outside of the function they were defined in.</p>
                </feedback>
            </choice>
</choices>

    </exercise>

        <exercise label="question8_7_2">
            <statement>
    <paragraph>Which of the following are local variables? Write them in the order that they appear in the code. <var />  <var />  </paragraph></statement><setup><var><literal_block force="False" highlight_args="{}" language="python" linenos="False" xml:space="preserve">numbers = [1, 12, 13, 4]
def foo(bar):
    aug = str(bar) + "street"
    return aug

for item in numbers:
    print(foo(item))</literal_block><paragraph>The local variables are</paragraph><condition string="^\s*bar\s*$"><feedback><paragraph>Good work!</paragraph></feedback></condition><condition string="^\s*aug\s*$"><feedback><paragraph>While aug is a local variable, it is not the first one in the code.</paragraph></feedback></condition></var><var><condition string="^\s*item\s*$"><feedback><paragraph>item is not a local variable.</paragraph></feedback></condition><condition string="^\s*.*\s*$"><feedback><paragraph>Incorrect, try again.</paragraph></feedback></condition><condition string="^\s*aug\s*$"><feedback><paragraph>Good work!</paragraph></feedback></condition><condition string="^\s*bar\s*$"><feedback><paragraph>While bar is a local variable, it is not the first one in the code.</paragraph></feedback></condition></var></setup></exercise>
    <exercise label="question8_7_3">
        <statement>

            <paragraph>What would be the result of running the following code?</paragraph>
            <literal_block force="False" highlight_args="{}" language="python" linenos="False" xml:space="preserve">x = 3 * 2
y = 1

def subtract(z):
    y = 10
    return y - z

print(subtract(x))</literal_block>

        </statement>
<choices>

            <choice correct='yes'>
                <statement>
                    <p>4</p>
                </statement>
                <feedback>
                    <p>Correct, the output is right because the subtract function takes in x as the global variable for the z parameter and puts it into the function. The subtract function uses the local variable y for its return.</p>
                </feedback>
            </choice>

            <choice >
                <statement>
                    <p>6</p>
                </statement>
                <feedback>
                    <p>Incorrect, look again at what is being produced in the subtract function.</p>
                </feedback>
            </choice>

            <choice >
                <statement>
                    <p>10</p>
                </statement>
                <feedback>
                    <p>Incorrect, look again at what is being produced in the subtract function.</p>
                </feedback>
            </choice>

            <choice >
                <statement>
                    <p>Code will give an error because x and z do not match.</p>
                </statement>
                <feedback>
                    <p>Incorrect, there shouldn't be any error.</p>
                </feedback>
            </choice>
</choices>

    </exercise>

    <exercise label="question8_7_4">
        <statement>

            <paragraph>What would be the result of running the following code?</paragraph>
            <literal_block force="False" highlight_args="{}" language="python" linenos="False" xml:space="preserve">def adding(x):
    y = 3
    z = y + x + x
    return z

def producing(x):
    z = x * y
    return z

print(producing(adding(4)))</literal_block>

        </statement>
<choices>

            <choice >
                <statement>
                    <p>33</p>
                </statement>
                <feedback>
                    <p>Incorrect, look again at what is happening in producing.</p>
                </feedback>
            </choice>

            <choice >
                <statement>
                    <p>12</p>
                </statement>
                <feedback>
                    <p>Incorrect, look again at what is happening in producing.</p>
                </feedback>
            </choice>

            <choice correct='yes'>
                <statement>
                    <p>There is an error in the code.</p>
                </statement>
                <feedback>
                    <p>Yes! There is an error because we reference y in the producing function, but it was defined in adding. Because y is a local variable, we can't use it in both functions without initializing it in both. If we initialized y as 3 in both though, the answer would be 33.</p>
                </feedback>
            </choice>
</choices>

    </exercise>

    <exercise label="question8_7_5">
        <statement>

            <paragraph>What would be the result of running the following code?</paragraph>
            <literal_block force="False" highlight_args="{}" language="python" linenos="False" xml:space="preserve">x = 9

def adding():
    x+=1
    print(x)

adding()</literal_block>

        </statement>
<choices>

            <choice >
                <statement>
                    <p>1</p>
                </statement>
                <feedback>
                    <p>Incorrect, pay attention to the local scope in the function.</p>
                </feedback>
            </choice>

            <choice >
                <statement>
                    <p>9</p>
                </statement>
                <feedback>
                    <p>Incorrect, pay attention to the local scope in the function.</p>
                </feedback>
            </choice>

            <choice >
                <statement>
                    <p>10</p>
                </statement>
                <feedback>
                    <p>Incorrect, pay attention to the local scope in the function.</p>
                </feedback>
            </choice>

            <choice correct='yes'>
                <statement>
                    <p>Error, local variable 'x' is referenced before assignment.</p>
                </statement>
                <feedback>
                    <p>This code gives an error because the local variable 'x' was referenced in the local scope before it was assigned a value.</p>
                </feedback>
            </choice>
</choices>

    </exercise>

    <exercise label="question8_7_6">
        <statement>

            <paragraph>What is a variable’s scope?</paragraph>

        </statement>
<choices>

            <choice >
                <statement>
                    <p>Its value</p>
                </statement>
                <feedback>
                    <p>Value is the contents of the variable.  Scope concerns where the variable is &quot;known&quot;.</p>
                </feedback>
            </choice>

            <choice correct='yes'>
                <statement>
                    <p>The range of statements in the code where a variable can be accessed.</p>
                </statement>
                <feedback>
                    <p>Correct.</p>
                </feedback>
            </choice>

            <choice >
                <statement>
                    <p>Its name</p>
                </statement>
                <feedback>
                    <p>The name of a variable is just an identifier or alias.  Scope concerns where the variable is &quot;known&quot;.</p>
                </feedback>
            </choice>
</choices>

    </exercise>

    <exercise label="question8_7_7">
        <statement>

            <paragraph>What is a local variable?</paragraph>

        </statement>
<choices>

            <choice correct='yes'>
                <statement>
                    <p>A temporary variable that is only used inside a function</p>
                </statement>
                <feedback>
                    <p>Yes, a local variable is a temporary variable that is only known (only exists) in the function it is defined in.</p>
                </feedback>
            </choice>

            <choice >
                <statement>
                    <p>The same as a parameter</p>
                </statement>
                <feedback>
                    <p>While parameters may be considered local variables, functions may also define and use additional local variables.</p>
                </feedback>
            </choice>

            <choice >
                <statement>
                    <p>Another name for any variable</p>
                </statement>
                <feedback>
                    <p>Variables that are used outside a function are not local, but rather global variables.</p>
                </feedback>
            </choice>
</choices>

    </exercise>

    <exercise label="question8_7_8">
        <statement>

            <paragraph>Can you use the same name for a local variable as a global variable?</paragraph>

        </statement>
<choices>

            <choice >
                <statement>
                    <p>Yes, and there is no reason not to.</p>
                </statement>
                <feedback>
                    <p>While there is no problem as far as Python is concerned, it is generally considered bad style because of the potential for the programmer to get confused.</p>
                </feedback>
            </choice>

            <choice correct='yes'>
                <statement>
                    <p>Yes, but it is considered bad form.</p>
                </statement>
                <feedback>
                    <p>it is generally considered bad style because of the potential for the programmer to get confused.  If you must use global variables (also generally bad form) make sure they have unique names.</p>
                </feedback>
            </choice>

            <choice >
                <statement>
                    <p>No, it will cause an error.</p>
                </statement>
                <feedback>
                    <p>Python manages global and local scope separately and has clear rules for how to handle variables with the same name in different scopes, so this will not cause a Python error.</p>
                </feedback>
            </choice>
</choices>

    </exercise>
        </section>
    </section>
</document>
